Here's something that I wish I knew
before I started using LMS for serious
projects, which is the more tools that
you give the LLM, the worse it performs.
I've talked before on the channel about
how LLM tools work, which is they're
just definitions added in via the system
prompt. You provide a title, you provide
a description, and you provide some JSON
schema with the things that the tool
needs to run. And then the rest of the
system prompt information just goes
below the tools. This works fine for
like six to eight tools depending on the
model. But if you have dozens and dozens
of tools, you're going to fill up your
system prompt really quickly with all of
these tool definitions. The reason this
makes it worse is that each of these
tool definitions is using up space. And
the more stuff you have in the context
window, the more issues you're going to
have with lost in the middle problems.
In other words, if you have like 50, 60
tool definitions or even as many as 12,
the LLM is going to have a hard time
figuring out which tool definition it
wants to use for any situation. So, when
you're working with tools, you really
want to make sure that only the ones
that are needed are in the system
prompt. And with MCP servers, it's
really easy to flood your setup with a
bunch of tools. Lots of apps like VS
Code and Cursor allow you to enable and
disable tools.